Osip Mandelʹshtam Papers, 1900s-1970s (bulk 1914-1937 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Letter from OM to N. Khazina (NM), 1919 December 5; 1; 1 folder (Folder 1)
- Letter from OM to N. Khazina (NM), original envelope, 1921 March 9; 2; 1 folder (Folder 2)
- Letter from OM to V. Ia. Khazina (NM's mother), 1921 May-June; 3; 1 folder (Folder 3)
- Letter from OM to father, E. V. Mandelʹshtam, 1923; 4; 1 folder (Folder 4)
- Letter from OM to father, E. V. Mandelʹshtam end missing -replaced from fol. 94, 1923-1924 winter; 5; 1 folder (Folder 5)
- Letter from OM to NM, circa 1925 October 1-4; 6; 1 folder (Folder 6)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1925 October 15; 7; 1 folder (Folder 7)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1925 November; 8; 1 folder (Folder 8)
- Letter from OM to NM, Sevastopol', cafeteria, 1926 January; 9; 1 folder (Folder 9)
- Letter from OM to NM, Leningrad), 1926 February 2; 10; 1 folder (Folder 10)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1925 November 11; 11; 1 folder (Folder 11)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February 5; 12; 1 folder (Folder 12)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February 8; 13; 1 folder (Folder 13)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February 7-8; 14; 1 folder (Folder 14)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February 9-10; 15; 1 folder (Folder 15)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February 12; 16; 1 folder (Folder 16)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February 12; 17; 1 folder (Folder 17)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February 14; 18; 1 folder (Folder 18)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 March 1; 19; 1 folder (Folder 19)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February 17; 20; 1 folder (Folder 20)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February; 21; 1 folder (Folder 21)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February; 22; 1 folder (Folder 22)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February; 23; 1 folder (Folder 23)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 March; 24; 1 folder (Folder 24)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February; 25; 1 folder (Folder 25)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 March 5; 26; 1 folder (Folder 26)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 March 7; 27; 1 folder (Folder 27)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 March; 28; 1 folder (Folder 28)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 February 27; 29; 1 folder (Folder 29)
- Letter from OM to NM, addition by "Ania" [A. Ia. Khazina], 1926 March; 30; 1 folder (Folder 30)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 March; 31; 1 folder (Folder 31)
- Letter from OM to NM -put in fol. 31, 1926 March; 32; 1 folder (Folder 32)
- Letter from OM to NM, Moscow, 1926 March 16; 33; 1 folder (Folder 33)
- Letter from OM to NM, Moscow, 1926 March 17; 34; 1 folder (Folder 34)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 October 1; 35; 1 folder (Folder 35)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 October 3; 266; 1 folder (Folder 36)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 October 9-10; 37; 1 folder (Folder 37)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 October 5-6; 38; 1 folder (Folder 38)
- Letter from OM to NM, addition by "Ded" ("Grandfather") [E. V. Mandelʹshtam], 1926 October 9-10; 39; 1 folder (Folder 39)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 November; 40; 1 folder (Folder 40)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 October; 41; 1 folder (Folder 41)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 November 5; 42; 1 folder (Folder 42)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1926 October 10-11; 43; 1 folder (Folder 43)
- Letter from OM to NM, original envelope, 1925; circa 1926 October 15; 44; 1 folder (Folder 44)
  [Envelope put with correct letter in folder 6] 1926 date likely by contents; postal cancellation stamp on envelope
- Letter from OM to NM, beginning missing, 1930 February; 45; 1 folder (Folder 45)
- Letter from OM to NM, fragment (p.7) -Put in folder 47, 1930 February; 46; 1 folder (Folder 46)
- Letter from OM to NM (pp. 1-6) Page 7 added from folder 46, 1930 February 24; 47; 1 folder (Folder 47)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1930 March 13; 48; 1 folder (Folder 48)
- Postcard from OM to NM, 1930 March 14; 49; 1 folder (Folder 49)
- (50) Letter [late 1930 May], four poems enclosed (1930 May), undated; 1 folder (Folder 50)
  1. Letter from OM to NMNote: Enclosed four poems, original OM's manuscripts replaced with copies in hand of NM, each dated -- 2., Apr.-May, Mne kazhetsia, my govorit' dolzhny..., no. ? -- 3. Ekhala konnaia, peshaia..., no. ?, 2 lines *, 1935 (on reverse of item 2) in pencil in hand of OM, undated -- 4. Idut goda zheleznymi polkami..., no. 513 -- 5. Den' stoial o piati golovakh..., no. 313 -- 6. Eshche my zhizn'iu polny v vysshei mere..., no. 302
- Letter from OM to NM, 1935 May 25-26; 51; 1 folder (Folder 51)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1935 May; 52; 1 folder (Folder 52)
- Letter from OM to NM, 1935; 53; 1 folder (Folder 53)
- Letter from OM to NM, contains one poem stanza: Mir dolzhno v chernom tele brat', no. 495, 1935 spring; 54; 1 folder (Folder 54)
- Letter from OM to NM original envelope added from fol. 58, 1935 December 26; 55; 1 folder (Folder 55)
- Letter from OM to NM, Tambov sanitarium, original envelope, 1935 December 27(postal canc. date), 56; 1 folder (Folder 56)
- Letter from OM to NM, Tambov sanitarium, original envelope, 1935 December 28; 57; 1 folder (Folder 57)
- Letter from OM to NM, Tambov sanitarium original envelope -put with correct letter in fol. 55, correct envelope added from fol. 88, 1935 December 29; 58; 1 folder (Folder 58)
- Letter from OM to NM, Tambov sanitarium, original envelope, 1926 January 1(postal can. date), 59; 1 folder (Folder 59)
- Letter from OM to NM, Tambov sanitarium, original envelope, 1926 January 2; 60; 1 folder (Folder 60)
- Letter from OM to NM, Tambov sanitarium, original envelope, 1926 January 3; 61; 1 folder (Folder 61)
- Letter from OM to NM, Voronezh, (letter 62 missing -- error in numbering?), 1926 October 30; 63; 1 folder (Folder 62)
- Letter from OM to E. E. Mandelʹshtam (brother), Voronezh, 1937 January 8; 64; 1 folder (Folder 63)
- Letter from OM to E. E. Mandelʹshtam, Voronezh, 1937 January; 65; 1 folder (Folder 64)
- Letter from OM to E. E. Mandelʹshtam, Voronezh, 1937 January 4; 66; 1 folder (Folder 65)
- Letter from OM to Iu. N. Tynianov, Voronezh, copy in hand of NM, 1937 January 21; 67; 1 folder (Folder 66)
- Letter from OM to V. Ia. Khazina (NM's mother), Voronezh, 1937 April; 68; 1 folder (Folder 67)
- Letter from OM to NM -- Voronezh (letter 69 missing), 1937 April 19; 70; 1 folder (Folder 68)
- Letter from V. Ia. Khazin to NM, 1937 April 19; 71; 1 folder (Folder 69)
- Letter from OM to NM, Voronezh, 1937 April 22; 72; 1 folder (Folder 70)
- Letter from OM to NM, Voronezh, 1937 April 26; 73; 1 folder (Folder 71)
- Letter from OM to NM, Voronezh, 1937 April 28; 74; 1 folder (Folder 72)
- (75) Letter, 2 enclosures (1937 April 30), undated; 1 folder (Folder 73)
  1. Letter from OM to NM, Voronezh, original envelope2 enclosures, both in hand of OM for passing on to V. P. Stavskii: 2. copy of excerpt from article in Voronezh paper by O. Krestova3. statement for V. P. Stavskii
- Letter from OM to NM, Voronezh, 1937 April 30; 76; 1 folder (Folder 74)
- Letter from OM to NM, Voronezh, original envelope, list of OM's poems on obverse in hand of NM, 1937 May 2; 77; 1 folder (Folder 75)
- Letter from OM to NM, Voronezh, original envelope- put in fol. 77, 1937 May 4; 78; 1 folder (Folder 76)
- Letter from OM to NM, Voronezh original envelope added from fol. 76, 1937 May 4; 79; 1 folder (Folder 77)
- Letter from V. Ia. Khazina to NM, 1937 May 4; 80; 1 folder (Folder 78)
- Letter from OM to NM, Voronezh, original envelope, 1937 May 7; 1 folder (Folder 79)
- Letter from OM to A. E. Mandelʹshtam (and NM), Vladivostok transit camp, original envelope: OM's last letter, 1937 November 30(post. canc. date), 82; 1 folder (Folder 80)
- Letter; postcard (1926 September 23-1931 November 11), undated; 1 folder (Folder 81)
  1. letter from OM to NM -- 2. postcard from OM to NM, Detskoe Selo, 1926 September 23( post. canc. date)
- Letter from NM to OM (unsent): her last letter to him, written to be left for him in case he returns from prison camp and she has been arrested, 1938; 1 folder (Folder 82)
- 2 postcards from OM to mother, F. O. Mandelʹshtam (1915 July 20-1916 July 20), undated; 1 folder (Folder 83)
  1. Koktebel', Crimea -- 2. Koktebel', Crimea
- Letter from E. V. Mandelʹshtam (father) to OM, fragment, in German, undated; 1 folder (Folder 84)
- Letter from A. A. Akhmatova to OM, July 12, no year; 1 folder (Folder 85)
- 3 letters and 3 telegrams from A. A. Akhmatova to NM (1957 March 15-1963 December 27), undated; 1 folder (Folder 86)
  1. letter, Leningrad -- 2. letter, no place given -- 3. letter, Moscow -- 4. telegram, Leningrad -- 5. telegram, Leningrad -- 6. telegram, Komarovo
- Postcard from M. I. Tvardovskaia to NM, original envelope, Moscow, 1972 November 7; 1 folder (Folder 87)
- 1 original envelope addressed to NM in hand of OM-put with correct letter in fol. 58, undated; 1 folder (Folder 88)
- 4 postcards from OM to NM (1925 October 17-1926 September 26), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 89)
  1. Leningrad -- 2. Khar'kov -- 3. note on money transfer form, Leningrad -- 4. Detskoe Selo
- Letter from OM to NM, 1935 April 18; 1 folder (Folder 90)
- Letter from OM to E. Ia. Khazin, Voronezh, 1937 April 10; 1 folder (Folder 91)
- Letter from OM to V. P. Stavskii, 1937 June; 1 folder (Folder 92)
- Letter from OM to Secretariat of Soviet Writers' Union, 1937 April 30; 1 folder (Folder 93)
  Regarding his situation and attitude of Voronezh branch of the Union, addressed to V. P. Stavskii, Voronezh
- Letter from OM and NM to E. E. Mandelʹshtam, fragment-put with letter in fol. 5, undated; 1 folder (Folder 94)
- Letter from OM to E. Ia. Khazin, Voronezh, 1936 April; 1 folder (Folder 95)
- Letter from N. Khazina (NM) to OM, 1919 September 17; 1 folder (Folder 96)
- 4 telegrams from OM to NM, all addressed to NM in Crimea, 1925-1926; 1 folder (Folder 97)
- Letter from NM to [OM], Kiev, 1919; 1 folder (Folder 98)
- 2 telegrams from OM to NM, both addressed to NM in Crimea, 1926-1927; 1 folder (Folder 99)
- Letter from "Tata" (NM's little niece) addition in hand of OM, 1920s-1930s; 1 folder (Folder 100)
- 6 telegrams from and to NM and OM (1934-1938), undated; 1 folder (Folder 101)
  1. telegram addressed to NM in Cherdyn', sender unknown (V. Ia. Khazina?) -- 2. telegram from NM to V. Ia. Khazina, regarding OM's mental illness, Cherdyn' -- 3. telegram from NM to V. Ia. Khazina, regarding OM's suicide attempt, Cherdyn' -- 4. telegram from NM and OM to E. Ia. Khazin, regarding movng to Voronezh, Perm' -- 5. telegram from OM to V. Ia. Khazina and [A. E.] Mandelʹshtam, Voronezh -- 6. telegram from OM and NM to E. Ia. Khazin, Voronezh
- Correspondence of NM, received (1912-1968), undated; 1 folder (Folder 102)
  1. letter from Ia. A. Khazin (NM's father) to NM -- 2. letter from Ia. A. Khazin to "son" [E. Khazin] -- 3. letter from Ia. A. Khazin to family -- 4. letter from Ia. A. Khazin to family -- 5. letter from Ia. A. Khazin to family -- 6. letter from Ia. A. Khazin to NM -- 7. letter from Emma [Gershtein] to NM, pp.5-8 missing -- 8. letter from Emma [Gershtein] to NM, p.2 missing -- 9. letter from V. M. Zhirmunskii to NM, regarding her dissertation -- 10. letter from Emma [Gershtein] to NM, p.2 missing -- 11. letter from V. M. Zhirmunskii to NM: regarding her dissertation -- 12. letter from Shishmarev to NM: regarding her dissertation -- 13. letter from Shishmarev to NM: regarding her dissertation -- 14. letter from V. N. Iartseva to NM: regarding her dissertation -- 15. letter from Z. Papernyi to NM -- 16. letter from Moscow City Council to NM: rejection of her application for housing in Moscow, typewritten -- 17. letter from "Liusia" [Merkulova?] to NM -- 18-20. 3 letters from Prostor magazine to NM: regarding publication of OM's poems, and royalties, typewritten -- 21. telegram from Makedonov family to NM -- 22. telgram from A. Akhmatova to NM -- 23. telegram from Voronkov to NM: regarding pension from Writers' Union -- 24. telegram from A. A. Akhmatova, "Nika," and "Varia" to NM; reply on top in NM's hand -- 25. telegram from A. A. Akhmatova, "Nika," and "Varia" to NM -- 26. letter from N. Shtempel' to D. Borisov: regarding copies of OM's works in NM's hand -- 27. letter from Ia. Ia. Roginskii to NM -- 28. letter from "Mark G." to NM: contains information on several people who were together with OM in Vladivostok transit camp and witnessed his last days -- 29. letter from Arthur and Inge Miller, typewritten, handwritten addenda -- 30. letter from A. T. Tvardovskii to NM, regarding manuscript of her book and edition of OM's poems; typewritten copy -- 31. letter from Kees Verheul (OM's Dutch translator) to NM -- 32. fragment in NM's hand
- Correspondence of NM (cont'd), letters received (1910s-1940s), undated; 1 folder (Folder 103)
  1-10. ten letters from Ia. A. Khazin (NM's father) to NM -- 11. letter from E. Ia. Khazin to NM, 1 sheet missing -- 12. letter from E. Ia. Khazin to NM -- 13. fragments of 2 letters to NM in hand of E. Ia. Khazin (?), signature missing -- 14. letter from "Boris K." [Kuzin] to NM -- 15. letter from "Boris K." [Kuzin] to NM -- 16. postcard from N. Khardzhiev to NM -- 17. postcard from N. Khardzhiev to NM -- 18. envelope addressed to NM, no return address -- 19. list of photographs on envelope in hand of NM
- Correspondence of NM (cont'd); documents (1938-1957), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 104)
  1. NM's labor record book -- 2. lease for V. Ia. Khazina's apartment -- 3-6. 4 telegrams from A. A. Akhmatova to NM, all adressed to NM in Tashkent -- 7. letter from D. Blagoi to NM -- 8. letter from "Viktor" [Shklovskii] to NM -- 9. NM's statement to the office of Procurator General: requesting reconsideration of OM's case, and his posthumous rehabilitation -- 10. letter from the office of Procurator General to NM: regarding above statement, request of additional information -- 11. letter from N. Khardzhiev to NM -- 12. telegram to NM, unsigned [from E. Ia. Khazin?] -- 13. letter to NM from "Edik," "Varia," and "L." -- 14-19. 6 letters from E. Ia. Khazin to NM, all in one envelope
- OM's documents (1925 October 19-1938 August 23), undated; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  1. OM's pass to Lenin Library reading room -- 2. OM's contract with Sovetskii Pisatel' publishing house about publication of his book on Voronezh -- 3. letter from Lenotgiz publishing house certifying OM's contractual engagement with it -- 4. OM's X-ray report -- 5. OM's pension book -- 6. doctor's note on OM's disability -- 7. X-ray referral note -- 8. doctor's note requesting neurologist to visit OM at home -- 9. receipt from Butyrskaia jail for money received from NM for OM -- 10. OM's certificate of temporary disability -- 11. doctor's note cetifying OM's heart seizure and prescribing rest fot two days -- 12. note from Writer's Union certifying OM's work on book about Voronezh -- 13. note certifying OM's stay at health resort -- 14-15. 2 prescriptions -- 16. letter from Armenian Trade Unions Council: in Armenian -- 17. OM's savings account book -- 18. permision by OGPU for NM to travel to Cherdyn' to live with OM, in exile there -- 19. OGPU document of OM's status in Cherdyn' exile -- 20. telegram to OM in Sukhum, unsigned
- OM's business correspondence (1926 July 20-1933), undated; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  1. letter from OM to V. Khalatov: first page of typewritten letter regarding publication of OM's book (title not specified) by Lenotgiz publishing house -- 2. OM's letter to Lenotgiz publisher: requesting return of Razgovor o Dante manuscript (rejected) -- 3. negative of above letter -- 4. letter from OM to Artemii B[atserievich], last name not given: requesting appointment to discuss OM's financial situation, handwritten fragment, addressee's memo on top in red pencil -- 5. fragment of OM's letter on his financial situation: typewritten -- 6. letter from OM to Tenerovich [Board of GIKhL publishing house]: requesting advance payment of 40% of royalties, handwritten -- 7. letter from GIKhL publishing house to OM: regarding translation project, typewritten, official letterhead -- 8. note to OM: regarding streetcar pass, handwritten -- 9. letter from Nikolai Arkhipov to OM
- Drafts of OM's letters regarding Eulenspiegel affair, undated; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  Four handwritten sheets, one double-sided, one with typewritten fragment of article on translations on obverse, 1928-1929
- ["Retsenziia na knigu Zhana-Rishara Blokha"], 1930s; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  Review of book by Jean Richard Bloch, complete draft in notebook, in hand of NM; for final version see Box 2, Folder 14
- Notes for book on Voronezh: handwritten sheets in hand of OM and NM, one sheet typewritten, one notebook, 1935; 1 folder (Folder 5)
- Fragment of essay; fragment of translation (1924), undated; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  1. Shum vremeni, essay "Khaos iudeiskii": fragment of copy in hand of NM, made in OM's lifetime -- 2. translation of poem [by Max Bartel?]: fragment, typewritten, circa 1924(on reverse of item 1)
- Printed fragments of OM's work; poems; loose fragments (1937), undated; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  1. Puteshestvie v Armeniiu: last two pages of printed text ( Zvezda No.5, 1933) -- 2. Slovo i kultura: four pages of printed text, first publication: Tsekh poetov, book 1 (Berlin: 1922), pp.75-78 -- 3. "Davaite slushat' groma propoved'...": first publication, printed text of 5 stanzas later divided in two poems: Opiat' voiny raznogolositsa... (no. 197) and Kak tel'tse malen'koe krylyshkom..., no. 139; collection Let, pp.25-26, 1923 -- 4. Charli Chaplin vyshel iz kino..., no. 386: typewritten -- 5-6. 2 loose fragments: one typewritten, one in hand of NM
- Photocopies of two letters from OM to NM (1926 March 5-1937 April 26), undated; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  1. letter from OM to NM: first page, for original see Box 3, Foler 26 -- 2.letter from OM to NM: for original see Box 3, Folder 71
- Photographs (1926), undated; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  1. of OM, copy of 1915-1916 photo -- 2. of NM, original, Yalta -- 3. of E. Ia. Khazin, ID photo -- 4. 2 unidentified photos, copies
- Kamen' (1910-1919), undated; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  Author's manuscripts and typescripts of poems written for OM's first book (1916), some poems not included in that volume: collated items, each in individual envelope, description on covers:1. V neprinuzhdennosti tvoriashchego obmena..., no. 498: author's manuscript2: I. Smutno-dyshashchimi list'iami..., no. 24: author's manuscript with corrections; on same sheetII. Kogda podymaiu..., no. 508 -- 3. Nezhnee nezhnogo..., no. 5: typed final manuscript, date in hand of OM4: I. Ot legkoi zhizni my soshli s uma... no. 43: author's draft manuscript, on obverseII. unidentified prose fragment, author's manuscript, apparently written around the same time -- 5. Pogovorim o Rime --divnyi grad... ( Rim), no. 56: author's manuscript (ink) with corrections (pencil) -- 6. Est' obitaemaia dukhom... ( Encyclyca), no. 71: author's manuscript -- 7. Poedem v Tsarskoe Selo!... ( Tsarskoe Selo), no. 35: author's manuscript -- 8. Medlitel'nee snezhnyi ulei..., no. 13: typed final manuscript -- 9. Ona eshche ne rodilas'..., no. 14: final typescript, date in hand of OM -- 10. V ogromnom omute..., no. 18, typed final manuscript -- 11. Dusha ustala ot usilii..., no. 15, typed final manuscript12. Kak ten' vnezapnykh oblakov..., no. 16: I. typescript, first version (N. Khardzhiev's note)II. author's manuscript, second version -- 13. Na perlamutrovyi chelnok..., no. 10, typescript with corrections in author's hand -- 14. Obraz tvoi muchitel'nyi i zybkii..., no. 30: author's manuscript -- 15. Ia nenavizhu svet..., no. 29: author's manuscript with corrections -- 16. Kogda udar s udarami vstrechaetsia..., no. 12: author's manuscript -- 17: I. Gde rimskii sudiia sudil chuzhoi narod..., no. 39: author's manuscript. II. "Azhurnykh galerei zamanchivyi prolet...": variant of first stanza of no. 39, author's manuscript -- 18. Tselyi den' syroi osennii vozdukh... ( Zolotoi), no. 36: author's manuscript (1912) -- 19. V stolitse severnoi tomitsia pyl'nyi topol'... ( Admiralteistvo), no. 48: author's manuscript (1913 May) -- 20. Zdes' prikhozhane --deti prakha... ( Bakh), no. 45: author's manuscript (undated) -- 21. Otravlen khleb i vozdukh vypit..., no. 54: author's manuscript (1913) -- 22. V taverne vorovskaia shaika... ( Taverna), no. 49: author's manuscript (undated) -- 23. V spokoinykh prigorodakh sneg..., no. 46: author's manuscript (1913) -- 24. Posokh moi --moia svoboda ( Posokh), no. 69 (1914). I. author's manuscript (1914). II. author's manuscript of first two stanzas; on obverse (undated). III. "Nominalism": prose fragment in hand of OM (undated) -- 25. Est' ivolgi v lesakh i glasnykh dogota... ( Ravnodenstvie), no. 62: author's manuscript (undated) -- 26. Letaiut Valkirii, poiut smychki... ( Valkirii), no. 55: author's manuscript (1914) -- 27. I ponyne na Afone..., no. 75: typed final manuscript, date in hand of OM (1915) -- 28. O svobode nebyvaloi..., no. 77: typed final manuscript, date in hand of OM (1915)
- Poems 1918-1914 not included in Kamen'; different versions of Kamen' poems, undated; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  Author's manuscripts and typescripts with author's corrections, collated items, each in individual envelope, titles on covers (1908 April 20)
  1: I. O, krasavitsa Saima, ty lodku moiu kolykhala..., no. 496: author's manuscirpt; contained inII. letter from OM to mother, Paris -- 2. Dovol'no lukavit': ia znaiu..., no. 499: author's manuscript -- 3. Slishkom legkim plashchem odetyi... ( Piligrim), no. 500 -- 4. ...korobki..., no. 502: author's manuscript, top left corner torn off --. 5. Kak chernyi angel na snegu..., variant of no. 145: author's manuscript (1910-1919) -- 6. List'ev sochuvstvennyi shorokh..., no. 503 (1910). I. author's manuscript, Helsingfors (1910 May). II. typed final manuscript (1910) -- 7. V moroznom vozdukhe rastaial legkii dym..., no. 183: author's manuscript (undated) -- 8. Ni o chem ne nuzhno govorit'..., longer variant of no. 11: author's manuscript, Helsingfors (1919 December) -- 9. Moi tikhii son, moi son ezheminutnyi..., no. 145, heading and date in hand of OM: "Rannie stikhi. Stikhi moi starye!" (Early poems. My old poems!): author's manuscript (circa 1919) -- 10. Muzyka tvoikh shagov..., no. ?: author's manuscript (undated) -- 11 (1910-1919). I. Skvoz' voskovuiu zanaves'..., no. 501: typed final manuscript (1919). II. Na temnom nebe, kak uzor ..., no. ?: final typescript, date in hand of OM (1910). III. Esli utro zimnee temno..., no. ?: author's manuscript (undated). IV. Besshumnoe vereteno..., no. ?: author's manuscript, Helsingfors (undated) -- 12. V izgolov'i chernoe raspiat'e..., no. 504: author's manuscript, St. Petersburg (1910 November) -- 13. Strekozy bystrymi krugami..., variant of no. 505 (stanza 3 omitted in final version): typescript, corrections in OM's hand (pencil) (1911) -- 14. Medlenno urna pustaia..., no. 506: typed final manuscript, year of date in hand of OM (1911 February 11) -- 15. Ia znaiu, chto obman v videnii nemyslim..., no. 507 (1911). I. author's final manuscript (1911 July). II. author's manuscript with corrections (undated). III. typed final manuscript (1911) -- 16 (1911). I. Dozhdik laskovyi, melkii i tonkii..., no. 504: author's manuscript on obverse of same sheet (1911 August 22). II. V samom sebe, kak zmei, taias'..., no. 162: author's manuscript (1911 August). III. V samom sebe, kak zmei, taias'..., no. 162: typed final manuscript, date in hand of OM (pencil) (1911) -- 17 (1911 July-August 7). I. Ty proshla tsaritseiu tumana..., variant of no. 175 ( "Ty proshla skvoz' oblako tumana...): author's manuscript with corrections; on obverse of sheet (1911 August 4). II. Ne sprashivai: ty znaesh..., no. 510: author's manuscript with corrections (1911 August 7). III. Ty proshla tsaritseiu tumana..., variant of no. 175 ( "Ty proshla skvoz' oblako tumana...): author's manuscript with corrections (different from manuscript above); on obverse of sheet (1911 August 4). IV. Dushu ot vneshnikh uslovii..., no. 156: author's manuscript with corrections (1911 July 1). V. Osennii sumrak -- rzhavoe zhelezo..., no. 149: author's manuscript (undated). VI. Ty proshla skvoz' oblako tumana..., no. 175: author's draft (1911 August 4) -- 18 (1911 November 12-1913). I. " Kogda sharmanshchika terpen'e..." variant of no. 159 ( Sharmanka -- zhalobnoe pen'e... ( Sharmanka): author's draft, fragment torn off (1912 June 16). II. " Kogda sharmanshchika terpen'e...": author's manuscript of first two stanzas (undated). III. Kachaet veter tonen'kie prut'ia..., variant of no. 27 (O nebo, nebo, ty mne budesh snitsia...) (1911 November 24). IV. V lazuri mesiats novyi..., no. 155: typed final manuscript (1911 November 12). V. Telokhranitel' byl otravlen...( Pervyi futbol), variant of no. 167 ( Futbol vtoroi): author's manuscript (1913) -- 19. Razveselilsia nakonets..., no. 177 (1912). I. author's manuscript, Saturday (undated). II. copy in hand of NM (1912). III. Gumanizm v Rime, author's manuscript, undated (on reverse of item 11) (undated)